so this is an excerpt from Magic
minakaya 35 the shorter discourse on
sachica here such a guy also known as
here such a guy also known as
the Buddha
how does Master gottama discipline his
disciples and how is Master Gotham as
instruction usually presented to his
disciples this is how I discipline my disciples
this is how I discipline my disciples
and this is how my instruction is
usually presented to my disciples
because material form is impermanent feeling is
material form is impermanent feeling is
impermanent perception is impermanent
determinations are impermanent
Consciousness is impermanent
bikus material form is not self feeling
is not self perception is not self
determinations are not self
consciousness is not self
all determinations are impermanent all
things are not self
are not self
so why does the Buddha
describe things as things as
um
not self rather than impermanent like
determinations
so why doesn't he describe
um
the things as not self sorry as as
impermanent uh like he describes the determinations
uh like he describes the determinations
as important right well because they
will be on the level of an explanation
it will be in the level like everything
is impermanent everything is not self
and then people would just use that to
basically paste it over their experience
and say hey everything is not self
everything is not self but the point is
to see it for yourself which means the
impermanence um and the not self are on two different
um and the not self are on two different
levels if you see it rightly
so you need to see the impermanence
rightly in order to experience the
nutshell but if you just think that not self is
but if you just think that not self is
seen where all this impermanence is seen
uh well you'll see that with yourself
with your sense of self
so that's why all determinations are
impermanent of all things are not self
not all determination implemented all
determinations are not self I mean all
terminations are not self but that's not
the Insight you need to see that in and
of itself would just be a just another
kind of information in the view you
could just adopt which is exactly what
people do today
you know I said everything is
impermanent you can see everything is
about this is not myself this is
impermanent that house is impermanent
this car everything is impermanent
everything's not health no everything is
impermanent I'm not myself
so that's then when you also have to
recognize that it's impermanence of
determinations of things that determine you and Define
of things that determine you and Define
you is not the impermanence of random
things in the scientific world
it's the impermanence of things that are
dear to you that you bound with that
your sense of self is generated by
so seeing that is impermanent means your
experience won't be taken as mind
so to understand the permanence you
don't um
um
like uh focus on Sensations in my knees
in the context well no just fine what's
what's there to you what would you be
afraid of losing and that's what
impermanence is like where where I find
gratification where I seek yeah pleasure
yeah where my sense of self-resides yeah
yeah just start undermining it by seeing
it that it has to sit on something
that's impermanent it has to be defined
by
so like when the Buddha spoke about a
king he was he was defined by his King's
possessions by his King's Army King's
wives King's palaces that is what makes
him a king
and you have to
allow that
um like yes that sense of self to arise
without acting out of it in order to
then be able to discern the
determinations of it well yeah sure but
you really need to start
you won't even be seeing the sense of
self and whether you act or not like you
need to First you need to sort of stop
looking for impermanence in the level of
observation like whether it's tactile Sensations or
like whether it's tactile Sensations or
sights and sound it's impermanent
impermanent and just to reflect and see
what are the things that you are sort of
attached to what are the things that are
there to you what were the things that
you'd be afraid of losing
those are the determinations that are
impermanent see they determine you for
what you are they determine the value
of things for you so that's what you
want to see as impermanent and thus it
cannot be yourself
and initially that's quite like scary so
for a king to see that I'm a king
because of what makes me a king yeah all
the king would need to do is just to
start reflecting that he could lose all
of those things including
he himself is a king wouldn't be no more
and if he does not develop his mind yeah
he's 100 but if somebody just starts to
practice then they'll not necessarily be
able to like just fully recognize it's
100 it's going to happen
but it would still be useful to even
just start thinking yeah I could see I
could already means ah okay so I can't
take this for granted and if it cannot
be taken for granted it cannot be myself
you cannot be my ownership I'm not the
master controller if it can change
against my will
so the king doesn't need to destroy his
palaces to to realize Anita he just
needs to start questioning what he has
taken for Ninja that's it what he's
taking us permanently yeah
and yeah because a lot of people think
like when I meditate it should be
pleasurable like it should be
um so so this is actually saying okay
there's this something
quite scary that yeah in this
contemplation and that's good that's
something which you should initially
yeah not well yeah that's why the
gradual training you don't just start
you sit down and you enter these
contemplations and so on like you get
sense restraint withdrawal from
unwholesomes professionality that will
give you the capacity to then hold these
uncomfortable things internally without
sort of you know looking away
immediately or trying to get rid of it
to cover it up or distract yourself from
it
yeah so I keep saying like you know even
whatever however you would have arrived at the
however you would have arrived at the
practice whatever meditation technique
you're doing really what you need to say
is like why am I doing this I'm gonna
start questioning that what am I like
okay so you're observing Sensations or
you know focusing on some objects and so
on is like what's the
what's the point of that do I know they
see was this supposed to result in
he come it calms me down calms me down
in regard to what
where does the disturbance come from so
that I need to practice calmness what is
it that disturbs me is it the fact that
I was
not focused enough
or is it affected
I'm holding dear things that are not in
my control and when I feel even the
slightest hint
at them perhaps changing or becoming
otherwise I'm overwhelmed with stress
and pain and and being unable to keep
the lid on it it's like oh but that's
the root of suffering not your lack of
focusing on undeveloped concentration
method no it's the wide basis of things
taken for granted is mine that cannot be
yours and you're turning a blind eye on
it and that's where you the stress is
building up the pressure at the edge
started languishing it and maybe nothing
able to perturb you
even if you never ever sit again in a
Lotus posture to meditate
and you relinquish it by seeing it
exactly by that contemplation okay wait
a minute yeah this is dear to me
is this in my control is it subject to
being otherwise all these things and
sustain those contexts don't ignore them
don't take them for granted and that is
relinquishing those things
there's that uh
I came across the other day the
translation well it's it's Alton cars
are other and it wasn't alien it wasn't
using the term Anita he was using other
foreign aliens which is in nature yeah
it's like all San Carlos are other
so all the things that are determining
myself other than myself whatever myself might
other than myself whatever myself might
be yeah they're alien to me
fundamentally they cannot be familiar
friendly personal deer they're alien
they're unknown they're not subject to
change they cannot be accessed
so in the core they remain alien to me
and that's why this sense of me and it
depends on that alien core well it's
equally alien to me and I think that's
it
which is alien to you foreign to you
other than you yourself depending on
that thing how is that is that is that a
good idea is that agreeable is that
trustworthy is that something you can
relax in and put your faith in no no because
in and put your faith in no no because
it's alien because it's unknown because
it's uncertain oh I don't know this
person I don't know this environment I
better be careful well that's the core
of your sense of self unknownable
because it's completely alien and
inaccessible so oh I better be careful
and not take it for granted but I trust
my body you know I've got good health I
feel as you know certain it feels
friendly familiar familiar yeah that's it
familiar familiar yeah that's it
familiarity due to negligence and
turning a blind eye
that's my familiarity mindfulness is
becoming familiar with the context of
that which is alien which is yeah become
familiar with what undermines your
day-to-day familiarity and that will not
be felt pleasantly initially at least
yeah you cannot
what's it a [Music]
yeah friendly familiar
and it says the opposite of all of that
yeah and that's how we take everything yeah
and that's how we take everything yeah
that's what I'm saying like so it's we
Define a practice contemplation of
nature you don't start on random things
that that you're impersonal towards that you
that you're impersonal towards that you
that you don't care oh you're a dead
bottle or that chair like nobody that's
like science yeah yeah but if that chair
has emotional significance you know it's
the left but your grandparents and it's
really valuable oh yeah then contemplate
the impermanence I have somebody come
and steal it
and see how you would feel on account of
that and then contain it contain that context
and then contain it contain that context
don't distract yourself towards
sensuality don't turn a blind eye
towards it and enduring that context
removes basically your dependence on things that
basically your dependence on things that
are alien
so it's diminishing your sense of self
that's it
do that sufficiently there will be
nothing in the world you can take as
yours because you can get rid of things
because as I said King Ken maybe destroy
his castle thinking that will free him
from his but he won't
because the ownership was not in those
things he was in your attitude towards
them which means he'll take something
else that's going to Define him
maybe he doesn't want to be a king
anymore but he's going to take another
definition of himself in other words his
self will find a way to get
re-established elsewhere yeah
yeah and this Insight isn't dependent on
yeah things changing it has nothing to
do with
the things in himself it's your
ownership of the things which is what
yeah with this difference between things
and determination exactly
and so then
uh
uh sachica or ajuicema then refutes the
Buddha saying
saying
a simile occurs to me master got him
just as when seeds and plants whatever
their kind reach growth increase and
mature all do so Independence upon the earth
all do so Independence upon the earth
based upon the Earth
and just as when strenuous works
whatever their kind are all done
Independence upon the earth based upon
the Earth
so too must have got him a person as
material has material form as cell and
based upon material form he makes good
and bad choices
a person has feeling as self and based
upon feeling he makes good and bad
choices and then he goes through five aggregates
and then he goes through five aggregates
and then the Buddha says
ajivasana are you not asserting thus material form
are you not asserting thus material form
is myself
feeling is myself perception is myself
determinations are myself Consciousness
is myself
and he then asks a counter question
what do you think
would a head anointed Noble King
exercise the power in his own realm to
execute those who should be executed to
find those who should be fined and to
banish those who should be banished
if you would exercise it must have
Master got him and he would be worthy to
exercise it
what do you think adivasana when you say
thus material form is myself
material form is myself
do you exercise any such power over that
material form as to say let my form be
thus and let my form not be thus and
then he goes through each of the five
aggregates so
a person can understand this
intellectually like
I don't have power
ultimate power over like form or feeling
or
um yeah any of these aggregates
what how does this insight
yeah three three one from suffering like
yeah exactly what I said before you have
to do it on
on the level of things
that are taking is yours
and the level of things that you do
assume the ownership over you know a
king can see whether he's in charge or Not by
can see whether he's in charge or Not by
trying to exercise power within his
kingdom not on someone else's Kingdom
then they wouldn't tell him anything
and that's exactly what people do they
try Okay formula but all those raps are
things they don't actually stand for
what the form is for what the feeling is
and that's why they're not uprooting
anything but obviously even sachika
but obviously even sachika
understood that he was referring to the
actual form yeah
so it's not that he was just this kind
of the self yeah that's why he wasn't
just like uh like a kind of sort of
abstract theoretical kind of just trying
to argue with a Buddha he was referring
to the form which which it is there
which it is the basis you know we've
been taking this off and so on it's just
that he thought see that form is always
there that feeling is always there so
whether you act like this so you act
like that that's all secondary to the
fact that
you are it yeah
but then they would say okay that form
that you do see rightly that's it like
that well what are the properties of it
can you make it not deform can you make
it not age can you make it not
experience elements and then he realized
oh he can't so then
you're not a king
if you if your king cannot exercise his
power and he's not a king somebody
else's or it's not his kingdom
so if you want to reflect that
um with like a with practical results as
I said needs to be done on the level of
your kingdom yeah on the level of things
that are dear to you that you assume the
ownership that you feel entitled to
words and justified in so oh now start
reflecting upon the form over there upon
the feeling over there upon the
perceptions over there
so
um seeing the five Aggregates in in the
way that sachica was doing
um is kind of like a necessary
prerequisite for then yeah looking at
the determination of that so exactly
yeah I think the problem is that people
as you said due to like
obviously it's been so long since since
the dhamma was kind of alive in the
sense Buddha was teaching it uh people
don't even know what the Aggregates are
so when you do the body Aggregates you
get these abstract Notions and then you
reflect on the level of abstract Notions
and then you proliferate further
interviews and that's exactly like I
don't know how many times I heard yeah
modern science has showed that proving
the Buddha right because look everything
is constantly changing or yes people
observing Sensations and trying to
pinpoint Anita and see and let go of yes
all of these are the kind of
proliferated abstract terms and Views
while in reality you're still bound and
attached with your central desires love
of children family company safety Health
taking life for granted all these vast
places that that you could really look
close not even that closely and you
would realize oh this is unownable but
it's completely ignored and then just
been kind of reinterpreted and
re-explained through these views and
yeah electrons changing the days of
Sensations coming and going oh that's
relevant that's not where your ownership
is that's not what your sense self is
that's all like on the secondary terms
so it's not even where the five
Aggregates are so to speak like you're
not I mean talk within the five decades
but you're not seeing them correctly as
a context exactly is that which
undermines you
and sachika does did see he sees that as
that which undermines whether you do
this or that feel this or that but then
he assumed that which undermines is
yours it's there it's stable
even if it's changing all the time at
least it is still mine yeah yeah he
wasn't obviously seeing it he wasn't
seeing the change on the right level he
was seeing the changes secondary to the
form to the feeling
and that's why he was regarding it as
permanent as mine as myself
but that's where we point out well okay
now that form that you refer to can you
prevent it
from deforming being subject to illness
the feelings can you can you make them
go away when you want and bring only the
ones you want no you are subjected to
them in the same way it's just like oh
none of that can do mine but you need
sense restraint and virtue to be able to
see yeah to reveal what is dear to you
you'll think okay I can control my
feelings I can eat a tasty cake and that
will feel yeah better but the Virgin
sense restraint would force you to to
stop turning a blind eye to what is dear
to you and actually feel the weight of
it and you know you're subjected to it
because oh yeah it's unpleasant
recognizing that these things are
subject to change why are you abound
with them
it's it's uh it's unpleasant it's what
anxiety is it's what suffering is it
wouldn't have been
Pleasant no if it was if you were not
born with him
but if you were in control of it or if
you were in control of them sure yeah
that's that suitable said monks would
you be upset if people come and start
collecting these branches and twigs and
burning them and stuff no no
we're not emotionally bound with them we
don't care about them
he said well so should you practice
towards your own body towards your
feelings those your aggregates
regarding same as these random things in
the world there's heaps
but in order to do that we have to undo
all those kind of uh bonds so to speak
in assumptions and and things you hold
there to you uh that you take for
granted so stop restrain stop acting out
and maintaining that assumed ownership
through your actions and then feel the
weight of it and sustain the context
and that's it the mind will have to turn
away from it
because you are providing the the
perception of a knee chain things that
the mind is bound with so it forces the
mind to turn away oh risk and it goes
away that's how you turn your mind from
assumptions and ownership you can just
decide it but if you clarify sustain and
cultivate that context day in day out
the mind will have to turn away because
it becomes unsuitable basis for
ownership so a suitable basis exactly
the suitable basis for ownership was
turning a blind eye
ignorance ignoring it that's it that's
all it took well that's the assumptions
were like
how do you know that form has your best
interest at heart you know why do you
assume it yeah that's that alien because
that is the mother earth you know I just
assume that it's friendly that it's for
me yeah because I can lift my arm I can
do I can I'm in control of my form yeah
it's a gift for Mother Earth yeah
yes even though she even nothing should
exist yeah no you're just selective
selective sort of um
it's like that assumption where you
assume that
the God is looking after you the in
other words you look after you it's all
for you with interesting it's all
fundamentally good but why do you jump
to that conclusion because you don't
know because you
at on some level you know that it is
other that you've got no access to that thing
that you've got no access to that thing
you've got no control of it so you can
feel the weight already I think most
people would feel the weight of it I've
been not in control on this
no it's all going to work out yeah yeah
so the weight of non-control is felt
and then it's too unpleasant to like
endure it sustain the context in regard
to it so it's easier to just then
slip back into the view oh but this is
all friendly and has my best interest in
heart and everything will work out we're
all heading to Heaven because you know
fundamentally we're all good and so on
but it's like no that's just the coping
mechanism because
maybe it's good see the fact is the
emphasis on maybe which means you can
never know so is it worth the risk
and then when you say say here it's good
it worked out well oh but how do you
know that that has worked that that will
work out well next
because fundamentally
things you are heading to no matter how
good everything else is is
sickness aging and death so
is that good is that going to be felt
lightly pleasantly and by the way it
doesn't mean like to solve sickness
agent that okay fine I'll do it well
when you're sick and dying means
everything that is dear to you in the
world on a kind of your senses your
children your family
your reputation your name your your
wealth everything else that you acquired
oh that's
that's now been taken away
so if you think you can handle death
we'll just check beforehand even while
you're alive and healthy
can you handle losing everything
right here right now just in mundane
sense not from a death point of view just if
not from a death point of view just if
somebody were to come and take
everything from you
would you be unmoved by any of that
assembly of the saw if they come on top
of your legs sure but you don't even
have to go that far just just take away
your car take away your house take away
your family take away stuff you're
you're familiar with
your mind be unmoved if you think
oh no well then you can only imagine
what death will do
how much it will move you because those
are the things that will be taken away
it's going to feel exactly like that
does contemplate sustain the context
practice sensor strain so you withdraw
yourself you withdraw the mental
dependence on those things while you
still can
and then when they are taken away one
way or the other well there will be no
no basis to undermine you because you
you know you removed yourself from it
the the simile of the of the on the tree
you're the top of a tree the fruit and
unless you come down when that tree is
being cut you will suffer a lot more if
you're high up than if you're kind of
halfway down or completely off of the
tree in the central domain yeah yeah if
you're yeah
not seeing the counterparts to the
central domain which is
the direction of where attention is
coming from it's the direction of sensor
strain and withdrawal and becoming
familiar with that
and the principle of simultaneity is
also important here is in terms of Wow
Wow sort of looking at yeah turning
sort of looking at yeah turning
as you know
the sense of self into an object it's
seeing what is dear to me and then
allowing that to endure in the sense
that yeah yeah that's the only only uh
the only correct way yes you can approve
the sense itself yeah some contemplate
not self and not self but yeah if it's
attended directly as an object it's it's
not it's not going to work
but if you attend to things that
yourself is emotionally bound with and
contemplates that impermanence without
ignoring the context of your bond
yeah well that's now I'm doing yourself